Finding Aid for Battle Creek Sanitarium [Miscellaneous brochures, pamphlets, etc.]
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
[Miscellaneous brochures, pamphlets, etc.] circa 1880-1950
Battle Creek Sanitarium
1 linear feet (in 2 boxes)
FF 4 B336 B863 (729)
Publications produced by or for the Battle Creek Sanitarium founded by John Harvey Kellogg in Battle Creek Michigan.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was assembled from a number of donors and sources.
The record group is open without restriction.
The Battle creek Sanitarium was founded as the Western Health Reform Institute of the Seventh Day Adventist Church in Battle Creek Michigan. In 1875 John Harvey Kellogg was named medical superintendent of the Institute and a year later it was renamed the Battle Creek Sanitarium.
The Sanitarium gained national prominence as "a place where people learn to stay well." Kellogg used the Sanitarium as a testing ground for the application of his "Battle Creek idea" on the effect of diet, exercise, correct posture, fresh air, and rest on the health and fitness of individuals. The program did enhance health. Kellogg and the Sanitarium prospered, despite policy differences with the Seventh Day Adventists, a 1902 fire which destroyed the building, and receivership debt due to overbuilding, until the 1930s Depression cut down patronage. In good times, Kellogg traded heavily on the celebrity of the Sanitarium's clientele to sell his health reform ideas. In hard times, he relied on the strength of the science which girded his system to keep pushing health. Throughout his sixty-seven year association with the Sanitarium, Kellogg never wavered in his faith in the rectitude of the "Battle Creek idea."
The collection consists of pamphlets, brochures, articles and other printed material on the history, philosophy and dietary practices, and treatments of the Battle Creek Sanitarium.
Subjects:
Battle Creek Sanitarium.; Hospitals--Michigan--Battle Creek.; Health resorts--Michigan--Battle Creek.; Kellogg, John Harvey, 1852-1943.
Contributors:
Kellogg, John Harvey, 1852-1943.
- Brochures, pamphlets, etc.
  - Added years of life and health circa 1940 (Box 1)
  - Battle Creek for rest circa 1920s, [15] p, [l] folded leaf; 25 cm. (Box 1)
  - Battle Creek for rest circa 1920s, [16] p.; 24 cm (Box 1)
  - The Battle Creek idea and its relation to healthful living circa 1940s, [16] p.; 27 cm (Box 1)
  - Battle Creek Sanitarium 1893, 7 p.; 22 cm (Box 1)
    (Reprinted from Chicago clinical review.)
  - The Battle Creek Sanitarium 1900s, 31 p.; 23 x 26 cm. (Box 1)
  - The Battle Creek Sanitarium circa 1930, 63 p.; 28 cm. (Box 1)
  - The Battle Creek Sanitarium: a short account of its aims and activities 1915, 31 p.; 23 cm (Box 1)
  - The Battle Creek Sanitarium: an institution utilizing all means, method and appliances for the treatment of the sick circa 1900, 72 p.; 16 x 22 cm. (Box 1)
  - The Battle Creek idea and its relation to healthful living circa 1940s, ,[16] p.; 27 cm. (Box 1)
  - Battle Creek Sanitarium 1893, 7 p.; 22 cm (Box 1)
  - The Battle Creek Sanitarium 1900s, 31 p.; 23 x 26 cm (Box 1)
  - The Battle Creek Sanitarium circa 1930, 63 p.; 28 cm. (Box 1)
  - The Battle Creek Sanitarium: a short account of its aims and activities 1915, 31 p.; 23 cm. (Box 1)
  - The Battle Creek Sanitarium: an institution utilizing all means, method and appliances for the treatment of the sick circa 1930, 72 p.; 16 x 22 cm (Box 1)
  - The Battle Creek Sanitarium dress system circa 1895, 32 p, 23 plates; 22 cm. (Box 1)
  - The Battle Creek Sanitarium diet list 1906, 46 p.; 16 cm. (Box 1)
  - Battle Creek Sanitarium ideas circa 1900s, 8 p.; 16 cm. (Box 1)
  - The Battle Creek Sanitarium, its buildings and guests: anniversary souvenir, 1898., [32] p.; 15 x 23 cm. (Box 1)
  - The Battle Creek Sanitarium: its work and its needs. circa 1903, 24 p.; 17 cm. (Box 1)
  - The Battle Creek Sanitarium Medical Missionary Training School 1898, 56 p.; 22 cm. (Box 1)
  - The Battle Creek Sanitarium: origin, purposes, methods. circa 1931, 32 p.; 24 cm. (Box 1)
  - The Battle Creek Sanitarium patients' directory circa 1800s, 45 p.; 9 x 16 cm. (Box 1)
  - The Battle Creek Sanitarium patients' directory circa 1800s, 46 p.; 9 x 15 cm. (Box 1)
  - Battle Creek Sanitarium: souvenir circa 1900s, 31 p.; 21 cm. (Box 1)
  - A brief account of the dedicatory services of the new main building of the Battle Creek Sanitarium 1904, 76 p.; 15 x 18 cm. (Box 1)
  - The building of a temple of health circa 1902, 28 p.; 15 x 18 cm. (Box 1)
  - Crane, Frank A sanitarium experience: what the Battle Creek Sanitarium really is circa 1900, 16 p.; 21 cm. (Box 1)
  - Dedication of the new sanitarium building and reunion of old patients December 18, 1884, 20 p.; 25 cm. (Box 1)
  - Description of the sanitarium at Battle Creek, Mich. circa 1880s, 31 p.; 15 cm. (Box 1)
  - Diabetes 1906, 23 p.; 16 cm. (Box 1)
  - Eating for efficiency circa 1900s, 29 p.; 21 cm. (Box 1)
  - Eating for health and efficiency circa 1900s, 32 p.; 20 cm. (Box 1)
  - Eating for health and efficiency 1928, 32 p.; 21 cm. (Box 1)
  - Favorite recipes of the Battle Creek Sanitarium circa 1900s, 37 p.; 29 cm. (Box 1)
  - Francis Grierson the famous English writer and world traveler visits the Battle Creek Sanitarium circa 1930, 15 p.; 16 cm. (Box 1)
  - The golden jubilee of the Battle Creek Sanitarium 1916, 167 p.; 24 cm. (Box 1)
  - A great philanthropic enterprise 1902, 4 p.; 37 cm. (Box 1)
  - A great philanthropic enterprise, [1902], 29 p.; 9 x 16 cm. (Box 1)
  - Grenfell, Wilfred
    - The soul of Battle Creek circa 1910s, 15 p.; 21 cm. (Box 1)
  - How King Edward got rid of his gout and escaped an operation for appendicitis. 1905, 12 p.; 15 cm. (Box 1)
  - How to add years to your life circa 1934, 32 p.; 23 cm. (Box 1)
  - How to use the Battle Creek photophore circa 1900s, 16 p.; 25 cm. (Box 1)
  - An inventory of vital assets circa 1900s, 14 p.; 23 cm. (Box 1)
  - An inventory of vital assets circa 1929, 30p.; 25 cm. (Box 1)
  - An inventory of vital assets, c1930 3, 30p; 25 cm. (Box 1)
  - An invitation to good health circa 1900s, [16] p.; 21 cm. (Box 2)
  - Keeping fit in fifteen minutes a day circa 1928, 29 p.; 28 cm. (Box 2)
  - Kellogg, John Harvey
    - The Battle Creek Sanitarium, an institution for health reconstruction: origin, purposes, methods 1928, 40 p.; 24 cm.+ (Box 2)
    - The Battle Creek Sanitarium, an institution for health reconstruction: origin, purposes, methods circa 1929, 28 p.; 24 cm. (Box 2)
    - The Battle Creek Sanitarium diet list 1916, 71 p.; 16 cm. (Box 2)
    - Health by training circa 1930, 15 p.; 26 cm. (Box 2)
  - Lake, George B.
    - The Battle Creek Sanitarium 1925, [6] p.; 25 cm. (Box 2)
      (Reprinted from Clinical medicine, September 1925.)
  - Life extension annuity bonds: an opportunity for safe and profitable investment 1927, 8 p.; 23 cm. (Box 2)
  - Life extension annuity service: a new form of investment 1927, 10 p.; 24 cm. (Box 2)
  - The measure of a man circa 1900s, [46] p, 22 cm. (Box 2)
  - The natural body trainer circa 1890s, 8 p.; 22 cm. (Box 2)
  - The new Battle Creek super solar arc lamp circa 1927, 17 p.; 26 cm. (Box 2)
  - The new dietetics 1904, 13 p.; 15 cm. (Box 2)
  - New fifteen story building now under construction circa 1920s, [10] p, [l] folded leaf; 25 cm. (Box 2)
  - New interesting and important facts in relation to diabetes: new and useful diet suggestions, [19-]; 31 p.; 16 cm. (Box 2)
  - Olsen, M. Ellsworth. The Battle Creek Sanitarium and its ramifications 1907, 8 p, 22 cm (Box 2)
    (Reprinted from Vegetarian messenger, December 1907)
  - One hundred new dishes for diabetic patients circa 1900s, 32 p; 15 cm (Box 2)
  - The philosophy of getting well: the chronic invalid likened unto a house on fire 1905, 16 p.; 15 cm. (Box 2)
  - Piper, Edwin
    - The triumph of truth: a morality masque 1916, 11 p.; 23 cm. (Box 2)
  - Program of special conference of state representatives of physical education and a two days' intensive school of physical education 1921, 59 p.; 23 cm (Box 2)
  - The reason why circa 1900s, 47 p.; 21 cm (Box 2)
  - The reason why 1911, 62 p.; 16 cm (Box 2)
  - The reason why: of the Battle Creek Sanitarium ideas about diet circa 1900s, 25 p.; 16 cm. (Box 2)
  - The reason why: of the Battle Creek Sanitarium ideas about diet circa 1900s, 46 p.; 16 cm. (Box 2)
  - Robinson, D. E. The Battle Creek Sanitarium: it's origin, development, ownership, and control 1943, 64 p.; 16 cm. (Box 2)
  - Rockwell, A. D.
    - The incandescent and the arc light in medicine 1909, 12 p.; 14 cm. (Box 2)
      (Reprinted from Medical record, December 18, 1909)
  - El Sanatorio de Battle Creek circa 1900s, [24] p.; 28 cm. (Box 2)
  - Sanitarium and hospital exhibits at the Columbian Exposition circa 1890s, 16 p.; 18 x 20 cm (Box 2)
    (Reprinted from National popular review.)
  - The School of Nursing department of the Battle Creek Sanitarium circa 1900s, [20] p.; 24 cm. (Box 2)
  - Starch and its relatives circa 1900s, 11 p.; 15 cm. (Box 2)
  - Starting life over at forty circa 1900s, 27 p.; 21 cm. (Box 2)
  - Summer at the Battle Creek Sanitarium circa 1900s, 31 p.; 23 x 26 cm. (Box 2)
  - Sunshine and health circa 1927, [15] p.; 29 cm. 2 leaves mutilated. (Box 2)
  - The therapeutic range of the electric light bath circa 1911, 31 p.; 13 cm. (Box 2)
  - The therapeutic range of the solar arc light circa 1912, 48 p.; 14 cm. (Box 2)
  - A visit: Francis Grierson, the famous English writer and world traveler, visits the Battle Creek Sanitarium circa 1900s, [28] p.; 25 cm. (Box 2)
  - A visit to the Battle Creek Sanitarium 1896, 16 p.; 17 x 22 cm (Box 2)
    (Reprinted from Good health.)
  - Vitamins in a nutshell circa 1900s, 32 p.; 15 cm. (Box 2)
  - The way out: of invalidism and inefficiency into joyous enduring strenuous health 1905, 31p.; 22 cm. (Box 2)
  - What some noteworthy people think about "Battle Creek ideas." [1919 ?], 23 p.; 20 cm. (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous flyers, advertisements, and recipes (Box 2)